<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cristian praiers &amp; godly meditatio[n]s vpon the epistle of S. Paule to the Romanes briefly conteyninge the summe of euery chapiter orderly, worthy to be vsed of al the faythfull in this wretched and sinfull time / translated out of Italian into English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1569</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16100</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2985.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1814</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22773899</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22773899</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25720</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16100)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25720)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1788:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cristian praiers &amp; godly meditatio[n]s vpon the epistle of S. Paule to the Romanes briefly conteyninge the summe of euery chapiter orderly, worthy to be vsed of al the faythfull in this wretched and sinfull time / translated out of Italian into English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[95] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted at London in Fleetestrete, at the signe of the Faulcon by VVylliam Gryffith, and are to be sold at his shop in S. Dunstones churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1569.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁸.</note>
                  <note>Title and each page of text within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans --  Prayers.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans --  Meditations.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25720:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Criſtian praiers &amp; godly meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vpon</hi> the Epiſtle of S. Paule to the Romanes, briefly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyninge the ſumme of euery Chapiter orderly, worthy to be vſed of al the faythfull in this wretched and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full time, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated out of Italian into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London by</hi> Wylliam Gryffith.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:25720:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25720:2"/>
            <head>¶<hi>To my right hartie freend,</hi> maiſter <hi>T. M.</hi> Thomas Beacon, wiſheth grace and peace from God in Chriſt Ieſu.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F howe great efficacie, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, ſtrength &amp; power chriſten praier is, both the ſentences, and hiſtories, of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture do aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly declare. For where at any time haue the faithful deſired of god by hartie prayer, wherin he hath ſuffered a repulſe? Praier geueth victory ouer enemies, deliuereth out of priſon, preſerueth in dangers,
<pb facs="tcp:25720:3"/> kepeth ſafe in fyre, mitigateth the wrath of God, obtaineth remiſſion of ſinnes, getteth euerlaſting lyfe, and purchaſeth for vs of God all good thinges, whether we reſpect the bodie or the mind. Euery true Chriſtian therfore can none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than highly delight in ſuch and ſo great a treaſure, wherof ſpring ſo many both neceſſary and profitable comodities to the vſer therof. And albeit there are already many godly praiers ſet forth in our Engliſh toung worthy to be frequented at al times of the faithfull Chriſtians, yet whan I had peruſed theſe prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers &amp; diligently conſidered the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of them, I thought it vnſeming to defraud my countreymen of ſo precious a Iewell. For in them they ſhall not onely learne to pray truely and according to the will of
<pb facs="tcp:25720:3"/> God: but alſo by the exerciſe of them they ſhall learne and commend to memory the whole ſumme of S. Paules Epiſtle to the Romaines, which Epiſtle in my iudgement is the principall parte of all the diuine ſcripture, foraſmuch as it containeth in a goodly order, yea &amp; that briefly, what ſoeuer is taught in the whole body of the ſacred Bible neceſſary for the inſtruction and edifying of a Chriſten man: ſo that whoſoeuer hath that Epiſtle &amp; vnderſtandeth the ſame, hath obtained the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the moſt neceſſary and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall partes of Chriſtian religion.</p>
            <p>Now to come by this thing, I meane, to get the knowledge of this ſo goodly and profitable Epiſtle, theſe prayers made vppon the ſame Epiſtle (which I haue cauſed to be imprinted for the profite of the
<pb facs="tcp:25720:4"/> readers) ſhall greatly helpe: ſo that they which exerciſe them ſhall get double profite by them. And would God ſome godly learned man wold take the like labour in making and ſettinge forth prayers vpon other partes of the holy ſcripture, as this authour hath done in this behalfe. For although I diſcommend not the prayers made by good and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute men (ſo that they be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the word of God) yet thoſe prayers which are made vppon the holy ſcriptures are moſt to be alow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed and vſed of the godly Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. For god can not diſalow that wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of his holy ſpirite is the Authour.</p>
            <p>Theſe Chriſten prayers &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meditations I ſend vnto you as a pledge and memoriall of our frend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip, nothinge doubtinge but that, according to your accuſtomed gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telnes,
<pb facs="tcp:25720:4"/> you will take them in good parte. Thus with right hartie thankes for your moſt hartie good will toward me, I wiſh you well to do. From Shene the xij. day of February in the yeare of our Lord. 1550.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25720:5"/>
            <head>¶<hi>Godly and Chriſtian</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations and praiers made vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon the Epiſtle of Sainct Paule to the Romanes.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the firſt Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Ieſu Chriſt, redéemer of the world, I thanke God through thee for all his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifites, and ſpecially for the great gift of our redemption by thée, which waſt borne of the ſede of Dauid after the fleſh, and are knowen the
<pb facs="tcp:25720:5"/> Sonne of God by the diuine power which thou haſt decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the whole world, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the bodies and ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſoules of the faithful with thy ſpirite, the which thou haſt communicated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly to mans genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, after that deſtroying our death with thy death, thou art retourned vnto lyfe for to be euerlaſting life of whoſoeuer accepteth thée for their onely Sauiour.</p>
               <p>O my Lord, graunt me ſo much of thy grace, that I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies may be in the number
<pb facs="tcp:25720:6"/> of thoſe. O Lord, the onely hope of my ſoule, cauſe me to know and to perceaue in the depnes of my harte, this thy vnſpeakable benefite. Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe in me thy healthful pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſo that I may know thée alwayes, as well the Sonne of God, as the ſonne of man. Heale the ſences of my bodie to thentent that to my eyes, eares, ſmelling, taſt and tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, all thoſe things may be abhorred which be contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie to thy holy lawe. Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie my ſoule and my ſpirite, that they may be a worthy
<pb facs="tcp:25720:6"/> habitacle of thy ſpirite. Make me, my Lord, to vnderſtand effectually the vertue of thy wonderfull reſurrection, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiuing me from day to day, and cauſing me to liue as dead to the world, and liuing to God: to whom with thée and the holy Ghoſt be glory.</p>
               <p>Lord God graunt vs ſo great loue of our ſaluation that alwaies we may remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber thée &amp; none other in our prayers. Geue vs ſo great deſire of thy glory that our ſoule may reioyce and render thée thankes through Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:25720:7"/> Chriſt, when the faith of the electes is ſéene in this darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the world. Geue vs ſuch perfection, that euery one of vs may ſerue thée with faith, and our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with charitie in our vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Graunt vs ſuch a taſt of the fellowſhipp of true chriſtians, that nothing may delight vs more, than to com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort our ſelues with them by mutuall faith. Grant vs ſuch light of thy ſpirite that we may vnderſtande our ſelues to be debteours for to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute frely to other the graces
<pb facs="tcp:25720:7"/> which by thee be geuen vs. Graunt vs ſo much ſtrength of ſpirite that we be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of the Goſpell of thy onely begotten Sonne: the which doctrine is accompted fooliſhnes to the wiſedome of the fleſh, but in veritie it is thy ſauinge power to euery faithfull perſon. For by it is reueled and communicated thy iuſtice, with faith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming betwene, the which is planted by thy ſpirite in the harts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elects, &amp; encreaſeth alwaies, &amp; bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth forth moſt ſwéete fruites of charitie.
<pb facs="tcp:25720:8"/> O father of mercies, graunt vs all theſe graces, that we may alwayes be knit in one ſpirite of faith and of charitie with Ieſu Chriſt our head &amp; thy Sonne, which with thée liueth and raigneth.</p>
               <p>I ſée my Lorde, by the grace that thou giueſt me, that the knowledge of thée which is gathered by the meanes of naturall perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, is not inough of it ſelfe to make vs good, ſith it is ſo that men by the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of viſible things crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted from the beginning, come
<pb facs="tcp:25720:8"/> into the knowledge of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting power &amp; diuinitie inuiſible, haue not glorified thée as God, neyther were thankfull to thée, but vainely wandering in their owne imaginations and makinge profeſſion of wiſedome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came moſt foliſh, in ſomuch that they worſhiped the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in ſtede of the creatour. Wherupon thy iuſtice, for to puniſh their vnthanckfulnes deth depraue them of all good iudgement, in ſuch wiſe that they embrace euill for good, &amp; ſewer for ſwéete. They haue
<pb facs="tcp:25720:9"/> defiled their bodies &amp; ſoules with all abhominable vices and vncleanes.</p>
               <p>O Lord god of my ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, kepe me and al thy faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full ſeruaunts from ſo great abomination, and from ſuch great blindnes. Grant vs O father of lightes, in ſtede of the darke light of our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the cleare light of faith, that we may acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thée truly, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thée euery one of vs, to loue thée, feare thée, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thée, putting al the hope of our ſaluation in thy mercy
<pb facs="tcp:25720:9"/> through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the ij. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> How great gods iuſtice and mercy is, we are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry redy to iudge, &amp; condemne other, not perceauinge that then we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne our owne ſelues, for becauſe that now with will and now in dede, we do thoſe thinges that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned by vs in our neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour, and plainely we know that after thy moſt iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, whoſoeuer ſinneth is worthy of death, and certein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:25720:10"/> we weare already all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to death euerlaſting if thy mercy &amp; pacience were not, the which forbeareth vs and calleth vs to repentance.</p>
               <p>Graunt vs perſeuerance, O Lord, to vnderſtand ſo great a benifite, and mollifie our hartes with thy grace, to the end that our hardnes and vnrepe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance do not encreaſe towards vs ſo much the grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter wrath in the day of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger when thy iuſt iudgement ſhalbe reueled, in the which thou wilt tender to euery perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to his doings
<pb facs="tcp:25720:10"/> that is, eternal death to thoſe which continuing in euill works &amp; reſiſting the truth, do prouoke againſt them thy furor. O lord ſuffer not that we, whom thy holy name is called vpon, be nombred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe, but for thy glory geue vs thy ſpirite, the which may teach vs to do thy will, and lead vs in the way of thy moſt holy precepes, to glory honour &amp; peace euerlaſting, through Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>When Ieſus Chriſt ſhal come to iudge the quicke and the dead, no body ſhalbe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:25720:11"/> to excuſe his vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes with the prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, becauſe that they which haue not had the light of the lawe written, haue not lacked the knowledge of good and euill by the lawe of nature: as clearly the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of euery on ſheweth, the which aloweth that is good, and reproueth that is euill. But I know my Lord, that the knowledge of the lawe without thy grace can no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing profite a man, becauſe he is not iuſt by the law. But who can obſerue the ſame? &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25720:11"/> our nature is ſo corrupt and peruerſe, that it ſéeth the bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter and taketh the worſe: wherby it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth to paſſe that many do know thy will and make profeſſion to rule the blind, to lighten thoſe that be in darkenes, to inſtructe the ignorant, and to vnderſtand thy doctrine and the veritie of thy lawe, and yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe teaching others they teach not them ſelues: they forbid theft and adulthy, and be theues &amp; adulterers, they ſpeake againſt Idoles, and be Idolaters, they glorie of
<pb facs="tcp:25720:12"/> the lawe, &amp; be tranſgreſſors of the lawe, and ſlaunder thy holy name, and cauſe it to be euill ſpoken of amongſt the wicked. Therfore to the end that we runne not into ſo great wickednes, and that the knowledge of the law be not to vs an occaſion of great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter damnation: write the ſame (O Lord) in our hartes by faith, and graunt vs ſuch grace that nothing may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>péere to vs either ſo good or ſo profitable or ſo delectable, as the obſeruation of thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements: that hauing
<pb facs="tcp:25720:12"/> our hartes circumciſed, wée may be thy true people, that our light may ſhyne after ſuch a ſort in the ſight of men that ſeing our good works e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of them may glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thee O heauenly father, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the iij. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>MY Lord, like as the naughtines of the Iewes was not ſufficient to make voyd thy faith of the noble promiſes made by thée vnto that people, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:25720:13"/> that thou art true and al men liares: ſemblably our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie can neuer be hable to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anull the faith of thy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which thy onely Sonne hath made to his faithful con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying to the ſame: I am with you euen to the conſumation of the world. Therfor although I ſée the ſame altogether vexed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and as a little ſhippe in the middeſt of the ſea bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of furious windes, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I am ſure that ſhe can not periſh becauſe that Ieſus Chriſt, according
<pb facs="tcp:25720:13"/> to his promiſe, ruleth and gouerneth her, and bringeth her at the length to the porte of eternall ſaluation. And how much greater our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes is, ſo much more commendable is his iuſtice the which forſaketh vs not for our deſerts, but defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs for his promiſe ſake.</p>
               <p>Ought we therfore to conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nue in ſinne to thintent that our vnrighteouſnes may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the iuſtice of Chriſt? nay, aboue all other thinges we ſhould abhorre ſinne, as that which of his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:25720:14"/> diſhonoreth Chriſt, and yet he by his goodnes &amp; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, of ſo euill ſede gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the fruite of his glory. Deliuer therfore, lord Ieſus, thy Church from all ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and from all iniquities, ſo that like as now by our ſinnes thou ſetteſt forth the faith of thy promiſes, ſo in time to come by our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we may glorifie thy holy name.</p>
               <p>My Lord, when thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt thy holy lawe to the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of Iſraell, they promiſed earneſtly to obſerue the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:25720:14"/> but afterward comming to the performance, they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo much of their promiſe, that one of the Prophetes ſpeaking of them, ſaith: that there is not one iuſt, or wiſe, neither that ſeketh after god. By the which thing it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite that all mouthes bée ſhutte, and all the world con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe to be giltie and to be thy debtour, becauſe that none ſhalbe pronounced iuſt by the workes of the lawe in thy iudgement, ſith it is ſo that the lawe doth not iuſtifie, but doth vs to vnderſtand
<pb facs="tcp:25720:15"/> ſinne: the which knowne lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth a man to deſperation if thy grace comforteth hym not. Therfore we thanke thée (O my Lord) with al our harte, for thy iuſtice, the which to put away our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes, thou haſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted to the world, beſides the lawe I meane the iuſtice which thou doeſt communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate by the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, to all them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, of all nations, for that without exception euery one hath ſinned and is deſtitute of thy glory, and whoſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:25720:15"/> is iuſtified, receaueth wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any deſeruing, the iuſtice of thy grace, through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrought by Chriſt Ieſu, whom fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euerlaſting thou haſt determined to bée by the meditation of faith, the propitiation of the world through his bloud, meaning to ſet forth thy iuſtice by the remiſſion of ſinnes paſt, the which thou haſt ſuffred for to ſhew thy iuſtice in the time of grace, to thintent that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one might knowe that thou art iuſt and the iuſtifier of euery one that beleueth in
<pb facs="tcp:25720:16"/> Ieſus Chriſt, the which with thée liueth &amp; raigneth world without end.</p>
               <p>My Lord, when thy ſaints do ſay that we be iuſtified fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly by the meanes of faith, many beleue that by the prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching of faith thy holy law is deſtroyed: but I through ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that thou geueſt me of my ſelfe, am conſtrained to ſay the contrary, that thy lawe is confirmed and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by fayth, ſith it is ſo that the man which is not iuſtified through faith, doth feare thée as a ſharpe and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous
<pb facs="tcp:25720:16"/> iudge, where as he that is iuſtified by faith, lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth thée &amp; worſhippeth thée as a father: the one as a moſt vile ſlaue ſerueth thée for feare: the other as a right lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſonne ſerueth thée for loue. Whereupon to the one thy commaundements do ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peare very greuous, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the other they be very plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſant. The one hauing the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirite of the world through the wiſedome of the fleſh lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth himſelfe and the world: the other hauing thy ſpirite by faith loueth thée and his
<pb facs="tcp:25720:17"/> neighbour for thy ſake: and the more faith encreaſeth, ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more groweth chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth al the obſeruation of the lawe. Therfore my Lord, encreaſe in vs faith, ſo that in vs may be eſtabliſhed and fulfilled thy holy lawe, to thy honour and glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the iiij. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> My Lord, if that noble <hi>Abraham</hi> could not glory in thy ſight y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his works, what ought I vnhappy ſinner to hope of
<pb facs="tcp:25720:17"/> my workes? Wherfore, like as he beleuing thy promiſes was fréele iuſtified by faith: ſo I beſech thée, that I may obtaine from thy mercy the frée remiſſion of my ſinnes, beleuing on Ieſus Chriſt. And like as <hi>Abraham</hi> recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the circumciſion of the fleſh for a token of the iuſtice of faith, ſemblably let me re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue from thy ſpirite the circumciſion of the harte, to thintent that I may ſerue thée in holines and in iuſtice all the dayes of my lyfe. And euen as <hi>Abraham</hi> receiuing
<pb facs="tcp:25720:18"/> the promiſe of poſteritie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable as the ſtarres, he doubted not through infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, neither be conſidered his bodie vnable to procreation by age, neither his wyfe which was baren by nature, but beinge ſtrengthned by fayth and truſtinge through thy word, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which he could not loke for by his naturall reaſon, he beleued that hée ſhould be the father of many nations, and geuing glory to thée, beleued aſſuredly that thou waſt able to perfourme that which thou haddeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed,
<pb facs="tcp:25720:18"/> which raiſeſt vp the dead, and with thy word ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt being to thinges which as yet be not: likewiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing me (my Lord) by thy mercy the remiſſion of ſinnes and to take me for thy ſonne &amp; alſo to geue me euerlaſting lyfe: graunt me grace that I thereof may not doubte through vnfaithfulnes, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther permitte me to behold ſo much my vnworthines, that I ſhould not faſten the eyes of my minde alwayes ſtedfaſtly vpon thy veritie, the which is more able to
<pb facs="tcp:25720:19"/> ſaue me, then my iniquitie to damne me, and geue me a fayth ſo ſtrong that hopinge through thy promiſe for that which I could not truſt for by my ſinnes, I may beleue by the merites of thy onely begotten ſonne, to become of the child of wrath, the child of grace and inheritour of eternall lyfe, and that I may render thée dew glory, beleuing ſtedfaſtly that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is impoſſible to thée, whom, though I be dead in ſinne, thou canſt reuiue with thy iuſtice. If my ſoule bée
<pb facs="tcp:25720:19"/> brought in a maner to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing through iniquitie, thou haſt power to geue it a being moſt noble and immortall, reſtoringe in it thy image. The which grace my Lorde I beſech thée that thou wilt graunt vnto me and to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy elects, through Ieſu Chriſt our Lord, the which by thy ordinaunce died vpon the croſſe for our ſinnes, and roſe againe for our iuſtice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the v. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>MY Lord, we are iuſtified through the liuely faith
<pb facs="tcp:25720:20"/> which thou haſt geuen vs, and be reconciled vnto thée, through Ieſu Chriſt our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer, which hath brought vs vnto his kingdome by the meanes of fayth. Graunt vs O Lord, grace to continue in thy grace, and augment in vs fayth in ſuch wiſe, that our ſoule may reioyce and glory, not onely in hope of eternall glory, but alſo in the tribulations of this preſent life, knowing for a ſuretie that tribulation worketh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience, and pacience probati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; probation hope, which
<pb facs="tcp:25720:20"/> deceaueth not, by thy increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible loue that thou heare beareſt vs (wherof the holy ghoſt rendreth a moſt certein teſtimony, which is geuen vnto our ſpirite) and the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thy onely begotten ſonne, the which, to obey thy will, died vpon the croſſe for vs miſerable ſinners and thy enemies, where as ſcarſe might be founde one that wold die for his frende either for one iuſt &amp; vertuous man. If therfore thy charitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs hath ben ſo great that while we were euill
<pb facs="tcp:25720:21"/> and wicked, Chriſt dyed for vs, much more now that we are iuſtified through hys bloud, we ſhalbe ſaued from thy anger by him: becauſe that being thy enemies hée hath brought vs in fauour with thée by his death, much more now being reconciled we ſhalbe ſaued through his life. O Lord God, write theſe moſt ſweete thoughts with thy finger in our hartes, that being crucified by thy grace, we may here glory that thou art our God and our father, through Ieſus Chryſt thy
<pb facs="tcp:25720:21"/> ſonne &amp; our redéemer. Amen.</p>
               <p>My Lord God, man was by thée created vnto thy i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage &amp; ſimilitude, that is, moſt holy, iuſt, and Lorde of the world: but he through his diſobedience became vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt, vngodly, deceitfull and ſeruaunt of the Deuill, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould this our miſierie euer haue had an end, if thy mercy had not ordeyned it from euerlaſtinge that thy onely begotten ſhould be the beginning, the middeſt, and thend of our ſaluation. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore we can not ſo much bée
<pb facs="tcp:25720:22"/> ſory for the ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> as we ought to be thankefull vnto thée for thy benifites, becauſe that, like as by <hi>Adam</hi> ſinne entred into the world and ſo death, euen ſo through Ieſu Chriſt is come vnto vs life, iuſtice and grace, a great deale more and of more force (which wée haue receiued from thy kindnes by Ieſu Chriſt) than the hurte that <hi>Adam</hi> hath done vs through his tranſgreſſion, becauſe that one ſinne alone hath con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demned vs, and the grace of Chriſt doth deliuer vs from
<pb facs="tcp:25720:22"/> many ſinnes. And if by the ſinne of <hi>Adam</hi> death hath reigned in the world, much more through Ieſus Chriſt life ſhall reigne in thoſe that receiue the aboundaunce of grace and of iuſtice which he geueth to the faithfull. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore like as the diſobedience of our firſt parents made vs ſinners &amp; worthy of eternal death, ſo the obedience of thy ſonne maketh vs iuſt and worthy of eternal life: And if afterward the lawe taking place ſinne dyd abound, the Goſpell comming after the
<pb facs="tcp:25720:23"/> lawe, grace hath much more abounded, to thend that like as ſinne hath reigned which leadeth to death, ſo now grace may reigne that iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth &amp; guideth ſuch as beleue vnto eternall lyfe, through Ieſus Chriſt thy ſonne and our redéemer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the vj. Chapiter,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Ieſu Chriſt my Lord, we are dead and buried in baptiſme and be riſen againe with thée as thy true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. Therfore my lord with thy ſpirite mortifie our fleſh
<pb facs="tcp:25720:23"/> and quicken our ſpirite, that we may liuely perceiue the vertue of thy death and of thy reſurrection. If our old man be crucified with thée, to thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent we might walke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward heauen in the newnes of lyfe, why in vs as yet do liue the luſtes of the fleſh which do drawe vs vnto the earth? Why do they not ſuffer vs to worke all that which the ſpirite deſireth? O our Sauiour, heare our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations and helpe vs for the glory of thy holy name ſake: and if we be verely
<pb facs="tcp:25720:24"/> thine, make vs in dede con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable vnto thy image. And like as death after thy gloryous reſurrection hath no more power ouer thée, but beinge deſtroyed by thée thou liueſt eternally wyth God, ſemblably we all being releued by thy grace, permit not (my Lord) that we be any longer maiſtered of ſinne which is the death of our ſoule, but graunt vs grace to liue alwayes to thée, and to ſanctifie our ſoules &amp; bodies to thy ſeruice, to thend that vnto thy honour may be ſet
<pb facs="tcp:25720:24"/> vpon the earth a reſemblance of that holy and bleſſed lyfe which we ſhal liue in heauen after the laſt reſurrection.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the vij. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>MY Lord, when I con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider the great cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of mans nature, on me cometh a horror and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible feare of my ſelfe, ſithens it is ſo that whyle thou leaueſt man in his dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and in his ignorance, he hath neuer true feare of thée, nor true knowledge of thy lawe, but may be well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb facs="tcp:25720:25"/> vnto fooliſh beaſtes, &amp; is verely like vnto them, and now thinketh that ſinne which reigneth in hym is dead, and it liueth. But when thou giueſt him ſuch perceue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunce that he is hable to ſée and to conſider to what thing the lawe bindeth him, then ſinne ſhewing forth his force declareth it ſelfe aliue, hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and very mightie, and man is knowne to be moſte weake and worthy of death, becauſe that the lawe is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tual and requireth the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the harte, and man is
<pb facs="tcp:25720:25"/> carnall and full of affections and of vncleane deſires. The lawe commaundeth that a man ſhould loue thée with al his ſoule, with all his harte, and with al his powers, that he put al his hope in thy mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie, and that he directe al his doings to thy honour: but man loueth himſelfe aboue all things, he dependeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on creatures, and is moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of glory, and for euery little trifle he is angry with his neighbour, and (as much as he can) perſecuteth him, whereas the lawe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:25720:26"/> him that he ſhould loue him as himſelfe. Finally the the law forbiddeth the deſire of the fleſh, &amp; the more it is forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo much more it war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth fierce, &amp; bringing forth fruite to death, encreaſeth damnation. Likewiſe ſinne which dwelleth in man, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an occaſion by the lawe that is holy and iuſt, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth more mightie and more pernicious, and by the lawe, in which is ſet forth iuſtice &amp; life, is gendred in man death and vnrighteouſnes. And while the power of the lawe
<pb facs="tcp:25720:26"/> laſteth there continueth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of man with thée and with the lawe. Let therfore (my lord) thy mercy be bleſſed the which hath brought vs from moſt greuous bondage of the lawe vnto the moſte pleaſaunt libertie of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and to the kingdome of grace, and in the ſtede of the face of Moyſes, which feareth, threatneth, curſeth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth, ſerueth vs the face of Chriſt which aſſureth, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth, and ſaueth vs, geuing vnto the faithfull the holy ghoſt, the which deliuering
<pb facs="tcp:25720:27"/> them from the yoke of the lawe, maketh them in loue with thée and with the lawe, that liuing iuſtly and holily vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, we may liue in Paradiſe eternally, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. We beſech thée my Lord, when that day ſhal come, and when this moſt greuous battayle ſhall end, that the ſpirite may not deſire againſt the fleſh, &amp; that the fleſh likewiſe may not deſire againſt the ſpirite: which eftſones maketh my life very bitter, becauſe I do not that which I would, but
<pb facs="tcp:25720:27"/> I do that which diſpleaſeth me. Albeit, it is not I that any longer in this wiſe do worke, but the ſinne that dwelleth in me, for that I know there dwelleth not in me, that is, in my fleſh, any goodnes. Then it is ſo that I haue a good will, but I can not do that good which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. Wherfore I do not that good which I would, but that euill which I wold not. And if I do that euill which I would not, it is but the ſinne that remaineth in me. This I ſay becauſe thy holy lawe
<pb facs="tcp:25720:28"/> deliteth me as touching the inward man, that is, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſpirite, the which is prone and bent to ſerue thée and to liue after the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of thy lawe. But I ſe an other lawe in my fleſh, that is, an other inclination that ſtriueth continually againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inclination of my ſpirite, &amp; maketh me priſoner and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt of the tyranous lawe of ſinne, the which is directly contrary to thy holy lawe. Wherby it cometh to paſſe, that like as my ſpirite is wholy geuen vnto iuſtice &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25720:28"/> to holines, and deſireth the death of the body for to liue with Chriſt, farre from the greuaunces of the fleſh: euen ſo my fleſh is delited with iniquitie, it feareth nor lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thée my Lord, neither geueth credite to thy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: it loueth the entiſements of the appetites &amp; the pomps of the world, neither wiſheth euer to come to an end of this mortall life. Vnhappy perſon that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from this defiled and ſinfull fleſh? from this mortal clod of concupiſcence,
<pb facs="tcp:25720:29"/> the which neuer giueth me reſt, but alwaies vexeth me, and continually fighteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my ſpirite. I yeld thée thankes my Lord, through Ieſus Chriſt, which with the ſacrifice of his fleſh hath pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged all the ſinnes of my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful fleſh, in ſo much that they be not imputed to me by thée to damnation. In the meane ſeaſon I liue after thy ſpirite and through liuely faith I am partaker of the moſt pure fleſh of Chriſt, which at length ſhall make my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible fleſh conformable to
<pb facs="tcp:25720:29"/> his glorious fleſh, and ſhall deliuer me from the body of this death, makinge that which is carnall, ſpirituall, after ſuch ſorte that all the luſtes and rebellings of the fleſh ſhall bée brought to nought, that all the parts of my body and of my ſoule and of my ſpirite might be pure, holy and cleane, and moſt re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>die to accompliſh eternally thy holy will.</p>
               <p>Therfore I that in times paſt was wont to ſerue with the mind of my fleſh to the lawe of ſinne, now with a
<pb facs="tcp:25720:30"/> mind renewed by thy ſpirite I ſerue thy lawe, my Lord: but with the remnantes of my fleſh, that is, of the olde man, I ſerue neuertheleſſe the lawe of ſinne, and do know my ſelfe ſo farre from the perfecte iuſtice of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lawe, that altogether I ſhould deſpayre of my ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if I did not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Ieſus Chriſt for my redemer and for my iuſtice. To him with thée be glory euerlaſtingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the .viij. Chapiter.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:25720:30"/>
               <p>MY Lord, my ſoule mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth for ſwetenes, when I read theſe moſte ſwéete wordes pronounced by thy ſpirite: that they be frée from all condemnation which be in Chriſt Ieſu, which do not liue after the fleſh but after the ſpirite, becauſe that the law of the ſpirite &amp; of the life which is in Chriſt Ieſu hath deliuered me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lawe of ſinne &amp; of death, ſo that now I am become by thy grace a member of Chriſt Ieſu, the which making a ſacrifice of his fleſh vppon the trée of
<pb facs="tcp:25720:31"/> the croſſe, hath deſtroyed ſinne and death, to iuſtifie &amp; to geue vs eternall life, that we ſhould not liue after the fleſh but after the ſpirite, becauſe that if we ſhall liue after the fleſh we ſhall dye, for that the affection of the fleſh is contrary vnto thy holy lawe and to the ſpirite of Chriſt, which is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of life. Mortifie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Lord, the affections &amp; appetites of our fleſh, that the ſpirite of Chriſt may liue in vs, the which now ſhall ſanctifie our ſoules with his
<pb facs="tcp:25720:31"/> preſence, and thou hereafter ſhalt make glorious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal our bodies in the laſt reſurrection.</p>
               <p>My Lord, if the people of Iſrael haue gloryed ſo much of the lawe, by the which they receaued the ſpirite of bondage that engendreth feare: how much more ought we Chriſtians to reioyce of thy goſpell, by the which we receaue thy ſonne, whoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite bringeth forth loue, and geueth vs boldnes to cal thée father. O my Lord, graunt me to taſte ſo much of thy
<pb facs="tcp:25720:32"/> ſpirite, that my ſoule may onely glory of this incompre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>henſible treaſure. Cauſe my lord, that thy ſpirite alwaies may render teſtimony vnto my ſpirite that I am thy ſonne, and conſequently thy heyre and coheritour with Chriſt, which through re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch and bitter death entred into the kingdome of glory and of life. Therefore my Lord, ſtrengthen my harte ſo that following thy ſteps I may boldly ſet thy croſſe before the honours and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the world and this
<pb facs="tcp:25720:32"/> temporall life, loking with pacience for the redemption of my body, and knowing for a ſuertie that the tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which be ſuſteined in this world for Chriſtes ſake, be not worthy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory which ſhalbe reueled vpon vs in the world to come. And for becauſe the inuocation of thy holy name is our onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge in our afflictions, and I of my ſelfe know not how to pray as it is mete, let thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirite (O Lord) helpe my infirmitie, direct my praiers: &amp; in my tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s comfort
<pb facs="tcp:25720:33"/> me, certifyinge me that like as to Ieſu Chriſt all thinges wrought together for the beſt when he ſemed to the world forſaken of thée: ſemblably euery thing hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the ſaluation of thoſe which loue thée, and be called by thée after the determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy good pleaſure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt appoynted from euerlaſtinge that thy children ſhould become con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the image of thy ſonne in the croſſe and in glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie, to thend that he might be the firſt begotten among
<pb facs="tcp:25720:33"/> many bretherne. If therfore (my Lord) thou haſt ſhewed me this fauour, to call mée vnto this brotherhod, why ſhould not I glory with my ſelfe in the croſſe of Chriſt, ſpecially knowing that thou iuſtifieſt them whom thou calleſt, &amp; doeſt gloryfie thoſe that be iuſtified by thée. And if thou be with vs, who ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be againſt vs? If thy charitie was ſo great, that to deliuer vs from death, thou haſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to death thy ſonne, how can it be that thou wilt not grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs with him al things?
<pb facs="tcp:25720:34"/> Who then ſhalbe ſo bold to accuſe at thy iudgement ſeat thy electes? If thou by thy mercy aſſoyleſt them and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteſt them for good &amp; iuſt: yea if Chriſt be dead to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them from damnation, and be riſen againe and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into heauen to make interceſſion for them, who ſhalbe hable to condemne them? And if thou haſt geuen vs ſo great and worthy ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of thy loue, who may make vs beleue that thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt vs not? Whether tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, miſery, perſecution
<pb facs="tcp:25720:34"/> hunger barenes, daungers, or ſwerd? yea I do beleue that all theſe thinges ſhall cauſe vs to be more certaine of thy good will towards vs, becauſe that through thy grace we ſhal ouercome, and in ouercoming let vs vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand &amp; be aſſuredly perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that we ſhall haue the vpper hand in all our temta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. I beſech thée, my lord, to confirme vs with thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite in this holy perſuaſion, ſo that euery one of vs may ſay with thy Apoſtle: I am ſure that neither death ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:25720:35"/> life, neither Angelles, neither princes, neither pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers, neither thinges preſent neither things to come, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther highnes, neither low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, neither any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhalbe able to ſeparate vs from the loue that God beareth vs in Chriſt Ieſu our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the .ix. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>MY Lord, when thy ſainctes do ſay that the predeſtination of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectes doeth not depend of mans workes but of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie,
<pb facs="tcp:25720:35"/> becauſe that onely they be ſaued which by thée be choſen through grace: the wiſedome of man can not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide this veritie, ſaying that this being true, thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be vniuſt, cruell and par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciall: As though that if a potmaker can make of one lumpe of clay ſome veſſelles to honour and ſome other to diſhonour, it might not bée lawfull for thée to faſhion of one ſelfe ſubſtaunce ſome men to perdition, which bée the veſſelles of wrath, in the which doth appeare thy iuſt
<pb facs="tcp:25720:36"/> iudgement, and ſome other to ſaluation, which be the veſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelles of grace, in whom is ſet forth thy glory. But the wiſe of the world ſay as plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth them. I for my ſelfe (my Lord) do render thée infinite thankes that it hath pleaſed thée that eternall life ſhould depend of thy mercy and not of mans will, becauſe that my corruption is ſo great, that I am ſure I ſhould go into perdition, if my ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did depend vpon me. And I knowe for a ſuertie that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one to whom it ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:25720:36"/> graunted by thy grace to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the knowledge of his vanity, wilbe of the ſame opinion, becauſe he is wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched which truſteth in his owne power, and bleſſed is he that putteth affiaunce in thy mercy throuh Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the x. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>MY Lord, I know by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that thy onely begotten ſonne Ieſu Chriſt, is thend of thy holy law, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he promiſeth lyfe to all the fulfillers, and curſeth the
<pb facs="tcp:25720:37"/> tranſgreſſoures therof. But how much more a man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth the lawe, and is enclined to obſerue the ſame ſo much more hée knoweth himſelfe for a ſinner, and doth deſpayre of his owne ſtrength. And for what end doth the lawe bring a man to deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? To this end that he might be conſtrayned to runne vnto Ieſus Chriſt the onely Sauiour, whereunto the iuſtice of faith exhorteth him, ſpeaking to him in this wiſe: O ſinfull man deſpeire thou not for thy vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:25720:37"/> for if thou wilte beleue with thy harte and confeſſe with thy mouth, that Ieſus Chriſt very God and very man, dyed for thy ſinnes, and is riſen againe &amp; aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for thy iuſtice, thou ſhalt be iuſt and ſaued. Graunt therfore (my Lord) for the glory of thy holy name, a liuely fayth to thoſe which be as yet vnder the lawe, that beleuing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing with harte and with mouth the Lord Ieſu, they may be iuſtified and receaue thy holy ſpirite, the which
<pb facs="tcp:25720:38"/> writeth the lawe in their hartes, and of ſeruauntes of the lawe maketh them thy children, and leadeth them by the way of good workes vnto eternall life, the which thou haſt promiſed to euery one that ſhall beleue in Ieſu Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p>My Lord, thou haſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſod that who ſo euer calleth vpon the name of Ieſu, ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſaued. But how be they able to call vpon the name of Ieſu, which beleue not in him? and how ſhall they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in him if they haue no
<pb facs="tcp:25720:38"/> knowledge of him? and how ſhall they haue the ſame, if thy goſpel be not purely prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched vnto them? and how ſhal it be ſincerly preached if thou ſend not faithfull prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers vnto them? Send ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Lord, preachers vnto thy people, &amp; open our harts with thy ſpirite, to thend we may liuely beleue thy word, and beleuing may call vpon Ieſu Chriſt our mediatour, and by calling vpon him we may be preſerued from thy anger, becauſe that without his protection, no liuinge
<pb facs="tcp:25720:39"/> creature ſhalbe iuſtified in thy ſight, ſith there is not geuen vnto men vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen any other name by the which they may bée ſaued, but the name of Ieſus our redemer, to whom with thée and the holy ghoſt be glory world without end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the .xj. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>MY Lord, we are thy faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, but greater is the number of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnfaithful. The which thinge may mineſter an occaſion vnto our fleſh to waxe proud, if thy ſpirite did
<pb facs="tcp:25720:39"/> not reſtraine it. Graunt vs therfore grace (my lord) that we may knowe our faith to be the gift of thy mercy, and not the reward of iuſt works which we haue done: So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ought not to put our affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce in our ſelues, but to feare, becauſe that if thou ſhouldeſt leaue vs in the power of our owne diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we ſhould fall into incre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dulitie: like as contrary wiſe they that be now vnfaithful ſhal beleue if they ſhalbe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited with thy mercy. O the depenes of the riches of thy
<pb facs="tcp:25720:40"/> wiſedome and of thy know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. How vnſerchable bée thy iudgementes, and thy waies impoſſible to be found out? And yet not withſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mans wiſedome preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to call thée in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to require the rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon of that thou doeſt. From this wicked preſuption kepe vs (my Lord) and graunt vs grace to bée fooles in this world, to thentent we may be wyſe in thy ſight, for that the wiſedome of the worlde is foliſhnes wyth thée, to whom be honour and glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:25720:40"/>
               <head>¶Vpon the .xij. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>MY Lord, graunt mée grace that like as thy onely begotten ſonne offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp in ſacrifice his fleſh vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon the trée of the croſſe for our ſaluation, ſemblably we may make a ſacrifice of our ſelues to thy glory, by mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying our will and our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the ſeruice of fayth. Wherfore let thy ſpirite liue in vs, the which permitteth not vs to be conformable to worldly men, but tranſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vs into thy image
<pb facs="tcp:25720:41"/> through the renuing of our mind, to thend that we may knowe and worke thy holy will, in the which conſiſteth felicitie &amp; perfection. Graunt my lord, that euery one of vs may be ſober, neither let vs preſume of our ſelues more then that which is conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, but humbly conteine our ſelues within our voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in exerciſing that talent faithfully which thou haſte geuen vs to profite our neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour. Giue vs (my Lord) a pure loue, to thentent wée may be louers of goodnes.
<pb facs="tcp:25720:41"/> Make vs feruent in ſpirite, diligent in thy ſeruice, paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in aduerſitie, continuall in prayer, louing and gentle toward our brethren, keping hoſpitalitie, glad with them that be glad, ſory with the ſorowfull, of one mind and of one accord: not proud and arrogant, but gentle and courteous to our inferriours: not ſclaunderous, but ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good example to al men: not contentious, but quiet: not reuenging, but ready to forgeue. Poure into vs my lord, ſo much ſwetenes of thy
<pb facs="tcp:25720:42"/> ſpirite, that euery one of vs may bleſſe and not curſe, pray for his perſecutours, &amp; not be ouercome of euill, but ouercome euell with good, recompenſing wrongs with well doing, that we beinge holy and perfect, through our perfection and holines thy holy name may be gloryfied.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the .xiij. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>MY Lord, I ſée many amonge Chriſtian people the which vnder the pretence of the libertie of the Goſpell (which is all ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all)
<pb facs="tcp:25720:42"/> do hide the licentiouſnes of the fleſh, and will not obey their ſuperiours: as though the powers being ordayned by thée, he dyd not reſiſt thy ordinaunce, and condemned not himſelfe whoſoeuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth power.</p>
               <p>Therfore we pray thée, my Lord, that thou wilt graunt vs grace to obey re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily the commaundements of our heads, the which now are not againſt thy ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, and make vs to render willingly that which is our dutie, to euery perſon, either
<pb facs="tcp:25720:43"/> reuerence, either tribute, ether honour, or what ſoeuer it be, that we may remaine in nothinge dettoures one to an other, but onely to loue together, becauſe that loue is the acompliſhment of the lawe. Behold now the night approcheth to an end, &amp; draw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth neare to the day of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lyfe. Therfore (my lord) ſend forth thy ſpirite that may clenſe our ſoules from the workes of darkenes, and put vpon vs Ieſus Chriſt thy brightnes, cauſing vs to liue after ſuch a ſorte, that our
<pb facs="tcp:25720:43"/> life may be a true reſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blance of him, to the honour and glory of thy holy name.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the .xiiij. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IESV</hi> Chriſt my Lord, I perceaue by the light that thou haſt geuen me, that I ought to accuſe me ſelfe, and not to iudge other: neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe I heare oftentimes the accuſation of my ſelfe, and do take vpon me wrongfully the iudgement of my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Therfore I hartely be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſech thée, that thou wilt vouchſafe to reſtraine this
<pb facs="tcp:25720:44"/> my preſumption wyth thy ſpirite, ſaying vnto my ſoule I was dead and am riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to be Lord of the dead and of the liuinge: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then iudgeſt thou thy brother? Speak theſe words O Lord vnto my ſoule, and make them to enter into the bottome of my harte, that in time to come I may forbeare to iudge an other, and attend to the conſideration of my ſelfe, lyuing in ſuch wiſe that I may not be condemned in thy iudgement, but be called to poſſeſſe with thy elects the
<pb facs="tcp:25720:44"/> kingdome of euerlaſting life</p>
               <p>My Lord, thy kingdome is iuſtice, peace, ioy in the holy ſpirite. Graunt vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fayth that iuſtifieth, and peace which pacyfieth the conſcience, and the ioy that ſweteneth the bitternes of the world, that we may know by theſe moſt precious giftes, that we are heires of thy kyngdome, &amp; may ſerue thée in iuſtice, peace, and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes all the dayes of our lyfe.</p>
               <p>My Lord, for as much as all that is not done in fayth
<pb facs="tcp:25720:45"/> is ſinne, we beſech thée that thou wilt geue vs ſo much ſtrength of ſpirite that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feare, neither hope, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tribulation, neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie may entiſe vs to do any thing the which we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue doth diſpleaſe thée, to the end that liuing in faith &amp; in feare, we may alwayes preferre thy holy will before all things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Vpon the .xv. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord Ieſu Chriſt heare our prayers, and poure thy loue into our hartes, that
<pb facs="tcp:25720:45"/> ſetting aparte all carefulnes of our owne commodities, we may procure with al our endeuour the profit and the ſaluation of others: like as to deliuer vs from the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of the deuil and of death, thou becameſt a ſeruaunt, &amp; taking vpon thée all our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, haſt cancelled them with thy bloud vppon the croſſe. And euen as thou ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt to ſaue not onely the people of God, but all other nations the which worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped falſe gods: ſemblably graunt that we may be beni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficiall
<pb facs="tcp:25720:46"/> and liberall toward our familiars and ſtrangers, toward our frendes and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, neither permitte any diſſenſion to riſe among vs, to thentent that by all men, with one ſpirite &amp; with one mouth together, the holy name of thy eternall father may be gloryfied. Repleniſh my Lord, with peace &amp; with ſpirituall ioy, our harts, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing in vs faith, that hope may abound in vs by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of thy ſpirite, the which leadeth vs by the way of loue vnto thy holy kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:25720:46"/>
               <head>¶Vpon the xvj. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>MY Lord, graunt vs grace to beleue, and without contradiction to obey the preachers of thy word, which do preach purely Ieſus chriſt and the Goſpell, and ſuffer vs not to be deceiued by prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chers which do come in the forme of ſhéepe and be raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Wolues, and wander about, cauſing diuiſion &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſes, as thoſe that ſerue not Chriſt Ieſu in the Goſpell, but their belly by falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and with the ſwéete
<pb facs="tcp:25720:47"/> venome of their wordes do corrupt the hartes of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple. Kepe vs my Lord, from the deceite of ſuch, &amp; graunt vs grace to be prudent and wiſe vnto good, and pure and ſimple as infants vnto euill, and treade downe ſhortly vnder the féete of thy fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, Sathan with his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, that thy goſpel may be ſincerely preached in all partes: the which thou haſt promiſed by thy prophets in the holy ſcripture, and the fulnes of time being come, thou haſte declared by thy
<pb facs="tcp:25720:47"/> Apoſtles to the whole world that whoſoeuer ſhal beleue: and be baptized ſhalbe ſaued, through Ieſus Chriſt our redemer: the whych with thée liueth and reigneth in the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt world without end. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:25720:48"/>
            <head>¶<hi>A prayer to be ſayd at</hi> the reading or hearing of gods word.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Eternall and moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God: whoſe word is the light vnto our ſteppes, and the lanterne vnto our féete: we moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech thée to illuminate our mindes, that we may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the miſteries conteined in thy holy lawe, and into the ſame ſelfe thing that we godly vnderſtand, we may be vertuouſly tranſformed, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> of no part we offend thy hygh maieſtie, through our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. So be it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25720:48"/>
            <q>
               <l>Vertit vt Chamaeleo corpus hirtum,</l>
               <l>Praeter albentes, maculas in omnes:</l>
               <l>Sic adulator tenet omne recté,</l>
               <l>praeter honeſtum.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of William Gryffyth, featuring a griffin (McKerrow 157)</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <q>· GEVE · GOD THE GLORYE NOWE · AND · EVER · MORE ·</q>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>¶<hi>IMPRINTED AT</hi> LON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don in Fléeteſtrete, at the ſigne <hi>of the Faulcon by VVylliam</hi> Gryffith, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in S. Dunſtones churchyard. 1569.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25720:49"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25720:49"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
